<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Calderwoods recantation: or, A tripartite discourse Directed to such of the ministerie, and others in Scotland, that refuse conformitie to the ordinances of the church. Wherein the causes and bad effects of such separation, the legall proceedings against the refractarie, and nullitie of their cause, are softly launced, and they louingly inuited to the vniformitie of the church.</title>
            <author>Scot, Patrick.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 59 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11615</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21857</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103208</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838965</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838965</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3358</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11615)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3358)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1219:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Calderwoods recantation: or, A tripartite discourse Directed to such of the ministerie, and others in Scotland, that refuse conformitie to the ordinances of the church. Wherein the causes and bad effects of such separation, the legall proceedings against the refractarie, and nullitie of their cause, are softly launced, and they louingly inuited to the vniformitie of the church.</title>
                  <author>Scot, Patrick.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 50 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Bernard Alsop, dwelling in Distaffe Lane, at the signe of the Dolphin,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Patrick Scot.</note>
                  <note>Signatures A3-4 missing in number only.</note>
                  <note>A fabrication by Patrick Scot.--British Library Catalogue.</note>
                  <note>Print blurred on title page and page 50.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Calderwood, David, 1575-1650 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of Scotland --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3358:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3358:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CALDER WOODS RECANTATION: OR, <hi>A Tripartite Diſcourſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>DIRECTED TO SVCH OF the Miniſterie, and others in <hi>Scotland,</hi> that <hi>refuſe Conformitie to the Ordinances of the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein the Cauſes and bad Effects of ſuch Separation, the Legall Proceedings againſt the <hi>Refractarie, and Nullitie of their Cauſe, are</hi> ſoftly launced, and they louingly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uited to the vniformitie of the CHVRCH.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Epiſt. Iam. cap. 3.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Vbi Zelus &amp; Contentio, ibi Inconſtantia &amp; omne opus pranum.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Bernard Alſop,</hi> dwelling in Diſtaffe Lane, at the Signe of the Dolphin. 1622.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:3358:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3358:2"/>
            <head>TO THE IMPARTIALL READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am not ignorant (impartiall Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) that to perſwade or contend for Redreſſe without Authority, little preuailes, and oft times expoſeth ſuch Motions to Contempt or Malice: yet the loue I owe to the Peace of the Church, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forceth me to ſollicite Conformitie in a matter of great conſequence. If any challenge my inſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encie, or intereſt; let them know, that I much more estimate the weake endeuours of good meaning, then the more learned ſhewes of Phariſaical Ostentation; That I am as well lyable to giue account of my Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, as the Arch Pillars of moſt profound Learning; and that armed with theſe Reaſons, I care not what the moſt Cenſorious Criticke or <hi>Thraſo</hi>-like Brag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gadochio can degorge againſt me. One fauor I craue, That thou wilt not curiouſly enquire what I haue beene, or pry into my former Errors (for which, I humbly begge pardon from the Mercy-Master in Heauen, and from his Vice-gerent, my dread Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne
<pb facs="tcp:3358:3"/>
vpon Earth) but conſider with iudgement what now I am, and how affected to the Truth. I haue in this enſuing home-ſpun Diſcourſe freely expreſſed my ſelfe touching the Controuerſies which haue long troubled the Church of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> In it I neyther wrong the dead, caſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt vpon the liuing; neyther leuell I at any mans perſon, further then, in the inquirie of Truth, may conduce to the aduancement thereof, and publike good. In this purſuit, I haue left all extrauagant Wanders, and balk'd all circulating Complements (too common both to Wits and Writs in this Age) and haue runne poſte in the high way; wherein if I haue ſtumbled, I expect leſſe harme, or more pitty. What I haue written, is without Art or Inſinuation; perhaps it may proue the leſſe gracefull: yet I hope it ſhall finde correſpondence in the mindes of thoſe that are not imbarked in partialitie, and loues the whole better then a part.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> 
                  <date>this <hi>29.</hi> of Nouemb. <hi>1622.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:3358:3"/>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>CALDER WOODS RECANTATION: Or, A TRIPARTITE DIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>COVRSE.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is fore-told of Chriſt, That in the latter dayes it ſhould be ſaid, <hi>Loe there, loe here is Christ;</hi> which by the Learned is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, not as if the Perſon of Chriſt ſhould be aſſumed and counterfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but his Authoritie and Preheminence, (which is to be Truth it ſelfe) that is to bee challenged; <hi>Ecce in deſerto ecce in penetralibus:</hi> Some haue ſought the Truth in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenticles and Conciliables of Heretikes and Sectaries; ſome, in the externall forme and repreſentation of the Church, ſome one way, ſome another: but the true Badge of the Church, and finding of Chriſt, is in Vnity, Peace, and Brotherly Loue.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:3358:4"/>Whoſoeuer then by contentious contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſies in matters indifferent, vnſwaddle the Church of her Bonds of Peace, are in the right way of diuiding the Vnitie of Spirit, to open a Gap to all diſorder and ſcandall, that thereby the weake may be brought to an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaintie of Religion, the peruerſe reiect it, or that the Enemies of the Church may make Muſicke by their diſorder. For this cauſe I am in good hope, that whatſoeuer ſhall bee ſpoken ſincerely, and modeſtly, for appeaſing the Relikes of ſuch controuerſies as diſturbe our Church of <hi>Great Britaine,</hi> but more ſpecially of <hi>Scotland,</hi> will be taken in good part, and be diſpleaſant to none. If any bee offended at this voyce, <hi>Vos estis fratres,</hi> you are Brethren, why ſtriue you? Hee ſhall giue a great preſumption againſt himſelfe, that hee is the party that doth his Brother wrong. I will not enter into the contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſies themſelues; they are ſo fore-ſtalled and determined by many more Learned Pennes, that whatſoeuer I might ſay, might ſeeme borrowed, or of leſſe weight. All men know and confeſſe, they are none of the high Myſteries of Faith, which detay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:3358:4"/>
the Church many yeeres after her firſt Peace; neyther doe they concerne that great part of the worſhip of God, of which it is true, <hi>Non ſeruatur vnitas in credendo, niſi eadem ſit in colendo:</hi> but wee contend about Ceremonies, Policie, and things indifferent. Let the offending ſide aggrauate their Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uances as they pleaſe, yet are they but Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies for which they haue ſo long conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and wherein no Holineſſe is put, other then Order, Decencie, &amp; Conueniencie; ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are theſe Ceremonies ſo much ſtood vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as due obedience to Superior Powers. If God tryed <hi>Adam</hi> with an Apple, it is enough; the ſinne is not valued, but the prohibition. <hi>Shimei</hi> was ſlaine for going out of the Citie; the Act was little, but the Bond was great.</p>
               <p>I will then firſt take a ſincere view and conſideration of the accidents and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of Church-controuerſies (at leaſt ſuch as concerne our ſelues to looke vnto) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt which I finde, that the imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections in the conuerſation of thoſe who had the chiefe place in the Church, and their miſ-gouernment, hath euer beene the prime cauſe of Schiſmes, and Diuiſions:
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:3358:5"/>
For whileſt the Gouernours of the Church continue full of Knowledge, and Good Workes, according to their Dignitie, and the precious care of Soules impoſed vpon them; ſo long the Church is ſituated (as it were) vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Hill; no man maketh queſtion of it, or ſeeketh to depart from it: But when theſe Fathers and Leaders loſe their Light, and that they waxe worldly louers of themſelues, or pleaſers of men; then doe men begin to grope for the Church, as in the darke; they are in doubt, whether they be the Succeſſors of the Apoſtles, or Phariſies. Howſoeuer they ſit in <hi>Moſes</hi> Chayre, yet they neuer ſpeake <hi>tanquam authoritatem habentes,</hi> becauſe they haue loſt their reputation in the Conſciences of men, by declining their ſteppes from the way they trace out to others; ſo that <hi>nolite exire</hi> had neede continually to bee beaten in the eares of men, ſo ready are they euery way to depart from the Church: For it is the pollicy of the ſpirituall Enemy, eyther by counterfeit holineſſe of Life to eſtabliſh and authorize Error, or by the corruption of Manners draw in queſtion Truth and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full things. This concerneth certainely the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:3358:5"/>
Biſhops to looke vnto; to whom I am wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe vnto my ſelfe, that I ſtand affected as I ought: No contradiction hath ſupplanted in me, the reuerence I owe to their Calling; neyther hath any detraction or calumnie imbeaſeled my opinion of their Perſons. I know ſome of them, who are moſt pierced with theſe accuſations, to bee men of great vertue; and for the reſt, I can condemne none. I know it is truely ſayd of Fame, <hi>Pariter facta atque non facta canit;</hi> their taxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions come not all from one Coaſt: they haue many different Enemyes; ſome, ready to ſlander them, ſome more ready to amplifie ſuch ſcandall, and ſome moſt ready to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue it: <hi>Magnes mendacij credulitas,</hi> Creduli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is the Load-ſtone of Lyes, and Enuie will creepe, where it dare not goe. But if any haue loſt their firſt Loue, if any be neyther hot nor cold, if any haue ſtumbled at the Threſhold in ſuch ſort, that they cannot ſit well that entred ill; it is time they returne whence they are fallen, and confirme the things that remayne. Great is the weight of their fault, <hi>&amp; eorum cauſa abhorrebant a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificio Domini.</hi> It is the weakeneſſe of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3358:6"/>
frailtie, rather to take poyſonable Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits out of Gold-gliſtering Boxes, then wholeſome Medicines from courſe cleanely Veſſels of Clay: But it were better wee had <hi>Elias</hi> Hunger, or <hi>Samſons</hi> Thirſt, in taking our Meat from a Rauen, or our Drinke from the Iaw-bone of an Aſſe, rather then to deface them, or caſt contempt vpon their Calling. The holy Angell would giue no ſentence of Blaſphemie againſt the common Slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer, but <hi>increpet te Dominus.</hi> It is noted in the Eccleſiaſticall Hiſtorie, That the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Synods, when they depriued any Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, neuer recorded the Offence, but buried it in perpetuall ſilence. <hi>Cham</hi> pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed his Fathers Curſe, for reuealing his Fathers diſgrace. Many good Fathers ſpoke ſeuerely againſt the vnworthineſſe of Biſhops: One ſayth, <hi>Sacerdotes nominamur &amp; non ſumus;</hi> another ſayth, <hi>Niſi bonum opus amplectaris Epiſcopus eſſe non potes:</hi> but theſe, nor no other, euer did put doubt of the lawfulneſſe of the Calling and Ordination of Biſhops.</p>
               <p>The ſecond cauſe of Controuerſies, is in multiplying of them by men, whom
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:3358:6"/>
the Church neuer wanteth; and who loues the ſalutation of RABBI, not ſo much in Ceremonie and Complement, as in inward Authoritie, which they ſeeke ouer mens Mindes, in drawing them to depend vpon their Opinion, and to ſeeke Knowledge at their Lippes: Theſe are the true Succeſſors of <hi>Diotrephes,</hi> Louers of Preheminence, and doe delight vpon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſort of Spirits, which doe adhere to them, <hi>Quorumque gloria in obſequio;</hi> ſtiffe Fellowes, who in zeale follow mightily after thoſe, vpon whoſe Oracles they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend; and are, for the moſt part, men of young Yeeres, or ſuperficiall Vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, or both, and carryed away with enticing apparencie of Singularitie, Goodly Names, and Pretences: <hi>Pauci res ipſas ſequuntur, plures nomina rerum, plurimi Magistrorum;</hi> the matter contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted, is leaſt thought vpon. Yet about theſe Controuerſies, are wreathed and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terlaced ſuch accidentall or priuate Emu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, and Diſcontentments, as ioyned together, breake foorth into ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, as violates eyther Truth, Sobrie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:3358:7"/>
or Peace: Some will be no longer <hi>ex nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mero;</hi> others ſide themſelues, before they know the right hand from the left; <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeunt ab ignorantia ad preiudicium,</hi> they leape from Ignorance to a preiudicate Opinion, and neuer take ſound Iudgement in their way: ſo that <hi>inter iuuenile conſilium &amp; ſenile preiudicium omnis veritas corrumpitur,</hi> when ſuch are indifferent, and not partiall, then is their Iudgement weake and vnripe through want of yeeres, and when it groweth to ſtrength, it is ſo foreſtalled by preiudicat opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, that it is made vnprofitable. Betweene theſe two, the Truth is encroached vpon, Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Powers contemned, and the Honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Names of Puritie, Reformation, and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline are trampled vpon and made the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects of contention.</p>
               <p>The third occaſion (as I obſerue) of our Controuerſies, is an extreme vnkind deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſome former Hereſie or Corruption, already acknowledged or conuicted. Vpon this Root, haue moſt of the Hereſies and Schiſmes of the Church ſprung, whileſt men haue grounded their Zeale, and meaſured the bonds of moſt perfect Religion, by the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſt
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:3358:7"/>
diſtance from the Errors laſt condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: but theſe be <hi>Posthumi Haereſium filij,</hi> He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies or Schiſmes that ariſe from the aſhes of ſuch as are already extinct. Some thinke it the true Load-ſtone, to try which Doctrine is good and ſound, by meaſuring which is more or leſſe oppoſite to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> be it Ceremonie, Pollicy, or Matter of Gouernment: yea, if it be matter of greater moment, that is euer moſt perfect, which is remooued moſt degrees from that Church; and that euer polluted, or blemiſhed, that participateth in any apparencie with it. But is it reaſon, I pray you? becauſe wee differ from the <hi>Roman</hi> Church in the adoration of the Elements, and ſubſtance of the <hi>Euchariſt;</hi> ſhall wee alſo abandon the reuerent, modeſt, comely, and commendable receiuing thereof vpon our knees? No: wee muſt keepe the good, and reiect the bad. It is a conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of much greater wiſdome and ſobriety, to bee well aduiſed, Whether in the generall demolition of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> (all mens actions being imperfect) ſome good was not purged with the bad? The Husbandman doth not diſclayme his heape
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:3358:8"/>
of Corne, becauſe it is mixed with Chaffe; neyther doth the Fiſherman refuſe his Draught of Fiſh, becauſe there is ſome Weeds in the Net; or doth God ſeparate himſelfe from the faithfull Soule, becauſe it is polluted with humane corruptions? It was the ancient cuſtome of the Fathers (ſaith <hi>Augustine</hi>) to approue rather then reiect the good things which they did find in the very Hereſies and Schiſmes.</p>
               <p>The fourth cauſe of our Controuerſies, I take to be the partiall affectation and imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Geneua</hi> and forraine Churches (a matter which in former times hath much troubled the Church:) for many of our Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, in the time of their Perſecution (as they call it) or rather Prodigals flight, hauing been conuerſant with the Churches abroad, and receiued a great impreſſion of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment there maintained, violently ſeeke to intrude the like into our Churches: But <hi>conueniamus in eo quod conuenit non in eo quod receptum est alibi,</hi> let vs not apiſhly imitate euery new coyned Cuſtome; <hi>Non quod opti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum, ſed e bonis quod proximum eſt eligendum;</hi> of good things, not that which is beſt, but
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:3358:8"/>
ſometimes that which is readieſt, is to be choſen. I wiſh wee might ſtriue with other Churches, as the Vine with the Oliue, which of vs beareth beſt Fruit; not with the Thiſtle and Brier, which of vs is moſt vnprofitable. Our Church in the Ile of <hi>Great Britaine</hi> (prayſed be God) is not to plaint: it is eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed and ſetled in the fulneſſe of Peace, in the ſinceritie of Doctrine, and in the Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Policie and Diſcipline: The Word is truely preached, by many godly, learned, and famous Paſtors, the Policie &amp; Diſcipline eſtabliſhed by the Ciuill Magiſtrat in former times in moſt parts of this Ile, &amp; now confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by a Religious and Learned King, who from his Cradle hath laboured to ſee the Church flouriſh in vnitie and peace. Shall then the affected paritie of a few, tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with wrong ends, diſturbe this Peace? God forbid: Or ſhall the Gouernment of the Church bee committed to the confuſed Synods, Presbyteriall Meetings, and Parochiall Seſſions of thoſe, whoſe Voyces are numbred, not weighed? <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia conſilia non minuunt malum ſed augent potius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:3358:9"/>The fift cauſe of our continued fierie Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, is the paſſionate and vnbrotherly practices againſt the perſons of others, for their diſcredit and ſuppreſſion. Firſt, the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratiſt goeth about to condemne the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of Biſhops, as an Hierarchie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining to vs of the corruption of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church: and then not finding footing in ſo ſinking a ground, he deſireth reformation of certaine Ceremonies which hee ſuppoſeth to be ſuperſtitious; as Kneeling at the receiuing of the Sacrament, Church-Liturgie, Muſike, the wearing of Surplus, and the like.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, they dreame vnto themſelues an onely and perpetuall Gouernment of the Church, which without conſideration, poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie, or foreſight of perill, muſt be erected and planted by the Magiſtrate; and heere ſome ſtay: Others goe further on, in fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing <hi>Knox</hi> his damnable Doctrine, and ſay, the ſame Gouernment muſt bee reared vp, maintained, and accepted by the people, at the perill of their ſaluation, without atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the aduancement thereof by other Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Authoritie then their owne: and from this Source floweth the inordinate zeale of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:3358:9"/>
ſome ignorant phantaſticall or ſingular and vnquiet Spirits, amongſt the Gentry and Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens, who in ſingular humors, for popular applauſe (with <hi>Simon</hi>) will be baptized with companie: But I wiſh ſuch remember, that in ſeeking Truth in Diſobedience, without Peace, at once they loſe Truth, Loue, Peace, their Adherents, and themſelues. Such coales of Zeale are like the Alchymiſts <hi>Elixar;</hi> about which much is ſpent, more talked, and it neuer brought to paſſe: Let the Quint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſence of your Wits be extracted, all your Obſeruations capitulate, all your Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments abſtracted, and all your Arguments vnited; all will end with great loſſe, and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh in ſmoake: You ſhall but by ſeeking ſuch Reformation, and bringing of Impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibilities into the Church, for matters triuiall hazard the ouerthrow of thoſe of greater weight and of peace for euer. But perhaps you will ſay, that the Biſhops maintayne as well Abuſes as good Ordinances, and that your reaſonable Demands are <hi>Vilipendit,</hi> or not anſwered: but I anſwere (as they haue formerly done to the like immodeſt Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge) That as there is no Element, which is
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:3358:10"/>
not through many commixtions depraued from the firſt ſimplicitie, ſo no Church euer breathed in ſo pure an Ayre, as it might not complayne of ſome thicke and vnwhole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome euaporations of Error, or Sinne. If you challenge Immunitie, it is rather pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption then true wiſedome. If too many ſinnes of practice hath thickned the Ayre of our Church, yet hath not one Hereſie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected it: There is no Calues in our <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel,</hi> none of <hi>Ieroboams</hi> Idolatrye. They confeſſe, that there bee many Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections in the Church, as Tares amongſt the Corne; which, according to the Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome taught by our Sauiour, are not with ſtrife to be pulled vp, but to grow together till the Harueſt. They grow not to an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute defence of all the Orders of the Church, or of the abuſe of good Inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; neyther doe they ſtiffely hold, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is to bee innouated, as if it would make a breach vpon the reſt. They know, that <hi>Leges nouis legibus non recreatae acceſeunt,</hi> Lawes not refreſhed with new Lawes, waxe ſowre. They are not ignorant, that taking away of Abuſes, ſupplanteth not good Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3358:10"/>
but confirmeth them; and that a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentious retayning of a Cuſtome, is as tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulent a thing as Innouation: Therefore, as good Husbandmen, they are euer pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and ſtirring in their Vineyard or Field, not vnskilfully or vnſeaſonably; yet haue they euer ſomewhat to doe. But in the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of theſe things, confuſed Paritie is not Iudge: Priuate Profeſſion is one thing, and publike Reformation another; euery man muſt doe that in the mayne, none this but ſuch of whom God ſayth, <hi>I haue ſayd you are Gods: Quis ſum</hi> is the queſtion of a good man; but <hi>Quis es,</hi> of an enuious Eye, that can ſee others, and not it ſelfe. Looke to your owne charge, in feeding Gods People committed to you, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing your ordinary Callings. Doe not like bad Husbands, gadde abroad to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens Houſes, neyther bee buſie Biſhops in other mens Dioceſſes: Set not your Teeth on edge with the ſowre Grapes of others. If the Rulers of the Church caſt not out Abuſes, and vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Ordinances, the ſinne is theirs; if a man vnworthy, enter, the ſinne is his:
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:3358:11"/>
But if you will not enter, becauſe ſuch a one is entred, the ſinne is yours: You ſhall not anſwere for other mens Faults, but for your owne Neglects; other mens ſinnes cannot diſpence with your dutie. There is a concin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of Members, and ſympathie of Affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in Gods Houſe: The Head muſt not deſpiſe the Hands, or other inferior Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers; neither theſe Members enuy the Head: you are to obey. Preſume not then vpon your owne Worth, or contend by Malice to ouer-rule; neither vpon your priuat Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie obtrude to the Church ſuch Gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which neuer had beeing, but in idle Speculation: Beleeue mee, Brethren, too much Preſumption gnaweth the Bones of the Spirit euen to the Marrow of Ignorance; and when Malice and Enuy are coupled with Preſumption and Ignorance, and are kindled againſt the Modeſtie of the Vertuous, the flame by reflection burneth thoſe that kindle it, and lighteth thoſe that are detracted, till they attaine to the path and poſſeſſion of Honor.</p>
               <p>To this former complaint you adde, that you are charged as if you did deny Tribute
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:3358:11"/>
vnto <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and withdraw from the Ciuill Magiſtrate the Obedience which is due, which you haue euer performed, and taught: I wiſh from my heart, you could cleare your ſelues of theſe too true ſuggeſtions. But the amplification of this Point falleth to bee in the ſecond part of this Diſcourſe, to which I leaue it.</p>
               <p>You ſay further, That Inquiſitions and Examinations haue beene too ſtrictly vrged againſt you: That the Biſhops are too ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in ſilencing ſuch numbers of you: That they ought to keepe one Eye open at the Good which you doe, and not to looke with both Eyes vpon the Euill which they ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe you doe; where now euery inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Word or light Eſcape is a Forfeiter of your Voyce and Gift of Teaching.</p>
               <p>Theſe bee the cauſeleſſe Complaints, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtly conceiued againſt your Mother the Church, and ſupreme Authoritie, who haue neuer ceaſed by Motherly loue and Royall fauours to reclayme you. But ſince fayre meanes cannot preuayle, and that your Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences are greater then your ſeruice, Iuſtice may change the Bonds of Recompence into
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:3358:12"/>
due puniſhment: The Warrants of all for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times hath allowed greater ſeueritie, then euer hath beene inflicted vpon you. Wiſe Generals puniſh mutinous perſons more ſeuerely then Robbers or Adulterers. <hi>Corah</hi> and his company were more feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully plagued then the Idolatrous <hi>Iſraelites.</hi> Who cannot rather ſuffer a lewd Seruant, then an vndutifull Sonne, though hee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend a fayre colour for his Diſobedience? When Nature offendeth Law, there Law may be iuſtly executed on Nature.</p>
               <p>You accuſe iuſtly Apoſtaſie and Sepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in others; and ſhall the Church ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the leaſt Seiſure in you? But if you hated your Sinnes more, and Peace leſſe, Prelacie would trouble you leſſe, and you not trouble the Church at all. But it is againſt my purpoſe, to amplifie Wrongs; I onely poynt at them, to mooue remorſe and amendment on the offending ſide, and not to animate ſeueritie on the other ſide, which is the ſtronger party; and who (I know) neuer (without griefe) did exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute thoſe Decrees againſt you, which Law and Iuſtice did enioyne: neyther haue
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:3358:12"/>
they affected any contentious Motion, or intended any Aſperſions, as Sectaries, Schiſmatickes, and Puritanes, againſt you; but contrariwiſe, in all courteſie and loue haue reputed you to bee Brethren and Sonnes of one Mother, the Church. Yet giue mee leaue to tell you, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though you haue not altogether cut your ſelues from the Body and Communion of the Church; yet doe you affect cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Cognizances and Differences, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you ſeeke to correſpond amongſt your ſelues, and bee ſeperate from it: But I wiſh you to vnderſtand, <hi>Tam ſunt mores quidem Schiſmatici quam dogmata Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matica.</hi> Saint <hi>Ierome</hi> telleth you, that <hi>Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſis Grece dicitur ab electione, eo quod ſibi eligat diſciplinam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You haue alſo impropried vnto your ſelues the Names of Zealous, Sincere, and Reformed; as if all others were Colde, Minglers of Holy Things, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, and Friends to Abuſes. You in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groſſe Chriſt and his true Worſhip ſo to your ſelues, that (as <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſayd to <hi>Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pianus</hi>) you will goe to Heauen alone.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:3358:13"/>
If a man be endued with rare Vertues, and fruitfull in Good Workes; yet if you ſay not <hi>Amen</hi> to your ſeuerall Poſitions, you tearme him in derogation, a Ciuill, Morall, or Politike man, if not worſe: Whereas the Wiſedome of the Scripture teacheth vs the contrary, to denominate men Religious by the Workes of the ſecond Table, becauſe the Workes of the firſt are oft times coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit, and practiſed in Hypocriſie. S. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſayth, That a man doth vainely boaſt, that hee loueth God, whom hee hath not ſeene, if hee loue not his Neighbour, whom hee hath ſeene: And S. <hi>Iames</hi> ſayth, That it is true Religion, to viſit the Fatherleſſe and Widow. So, that which with you is but Phyloſophicall, is with the Apoſtles true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; and contentious ſtriuing, which you doe account Religion and Zeale, is with the Apoſtle holden Wickedneſſe: But remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that there is a like Woe to them that ſpeake good of euill, as to thoſe that ſpeake euill of good.</p>
               <p>If a Biſhop or Preacher preach with care and meditation, ordering the matter they handle, ſoundly and diſtinctly for memory,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:3358:13"/>
deducing and drawing it for direction, and authorizing it with ſtrong Warrants: Some of you haue cenſured ſuch Doctrine as a forme of ſpeaking, not becomming the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitie of the Goſpell, preferring it to the reprehenſion of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> ſpeaking of the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticing ſpeeches of mans Wiſedome. But be not deceiued with ſuch vncharitable cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: woe were to all the World, if Chriſt ſhould tye his preſence onely to your faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; or leaue learned peaceable Spirits, and make his reſidence with Raylers. As to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend iuſtly, requireth a due diſcretion; ſo to detract iniuriouſly, in a Great man is ſtayne of Honor, in a Learned man a note of Irreligion, and in all ſorts of men a plague of Nature, ariſing from the thought of a corrupt, vnbridled, and ſinfull heart. If ſuch of you ſay, that you exclayme a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt none, but againſt thoſe that haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued it, it is in that I taxe your indiſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: for whoſoeuer diſgraceth publikely, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee hath reprooued priuately, may be a good <hi>Ariſtarchus,</hi> but no good Chriſtian. If your owne manner of Preaching were exactly examined (I ſpeake not of all, but of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:3358:14"/>
moſt) what is it? You exhort well, worke compunction of Minde, and bring Men well to the queſtion, <hi>Viri fratres quid age<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus;</hi> Men and Brethren, what ſhall wee doe? But that is not enough, except you reſolue the queſtion. The greateſt part of your time allotted for Sermon, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps an houre or two more, is ſpent vpon Controuerſies, or rayling vpon particular perſons for euery miſ-conceited Diſcontent: but God knoweth you handle Controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies weakely, and Obiter, as before a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that will accept of any thing as Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, that commeth from you. But the Word, the Bread of Life, muſt not bee wreſted, neyther toſſed vp and downe: it muſt be broken, and Directions drawne <hi>ad caſus Conſcientiae,</hi> that men may be war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted thereby in their particular Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. And this, many of you are not able to performe, through want of grounded Knowledge, Study, and Time; your Labours, for the moſt part, bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing imployed vpon needleſſe Controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, and vpholding of Factious Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:3358:14"/>Againe, you carry not an equall hand in teaching the people their lawfull Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, as well as their Reſtraints and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibitions: You thinke a man cannot goe too farre in that, which hath a ſhew of a Commaundement; you forget, that there bee ſinnes on the right hand, as well as on the left hand; and that the Word is two-edged, and cutteth on both ſides, as well the ſuperſtitious Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance, as the prophane Tranſgreſſion. Who doubteth, but it is as vnlawfull to ſhut where God hath opened, as to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen where God hath ſhut? To binde where God hath looſed, as to looſe where God hath bound? Amongſt Men it is commonly as ill taken, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne backe Fauours, as to diſobey Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands.</p>
               <p>Another Point of great inconuenience and perill is, That you entitle the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to heare Controuerſies in all Points of Doctrine; alledging, That there is no part of Gods Councell ought to bee ſuppreſſed, or the People defrauded: ſo
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:3358:15"/>
as the difference which the Apoſtle maketh betwixt ſtrong Meat and Milke, is confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and the Precept that the weake are not to be admitted to Controuerſies, taketh no effect; and which is a greater Seminarie of further Euils (whileſt you ſeeke to expreſſe Scripture for euery thing, and haue depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued your ſelues of a ſpeciall helpe, by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beazeling the Authority of the Fathers) you reſort to naked Examples, conceited Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, and forced Alluſions, which enure men to all vncertaintie of Religion.</p>
               <p>Another Extremitie you vſe, in magnify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your Preaching; which I graunt, is an holy Inſtitution, and powerfull meanes to ſaluation: yet hath it Limits, as all things elſe haue. Whereſoeuer you finde in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture mention of the Word, you expound it of Preaching, which you haue made in a manner of the Eſſence of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per; as if it could not be effectuall, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Sermon going before: and this hath beene ſpecially grieuous to many hungry Soules, who vpon their Death-Beddes, with groanes, haue deſired ſo precious a Foode.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:3358:15"/>The other holy Sacrament of Baptiſme you haue ſometimes tyed to bee miniſtred onely in the Church, and vpon Sundayes; ſometimes you haue reſtrayned it for the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the Fathers, they being brethren of your owne Congregation: by which rare vncharitable inuention, thouſands of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren haue dyed in your default, without the Seale of their Saluation, preſcribed by Chriſt.</p>
               <p>You doe annihilate Church-Liturgies and ſet formes of Diuine Worſhip, and both in your Sermons and Prayers onely magnifie your extemporarie Conceptions or Reuela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions (as you ſometimes name them) euery day bringeth new Conceits, and one day doth not teach, but correct another. In the meane time, what Preaching is, or who may be ſayd to preach, you make no queſtion: but ſure I am, that many of you that call hotely for a Preaching Miniſter, are the firſt that ought to be ſequeſtred from ſo holy a Function.</p>
               <p>Theſe Errors and miſ-proceedings you doe fortifie and intrench, by being addicted to your owne Opinions, and impatient to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:3358:16"/>
heare contradiction, or arguments, that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaud not your humors. I know ſome of you thinke it a tempting of God, to heare or reade that, which with good reaſon may bee ſayd or written againſt you; as if there were <hi>a quod bonum eſt tenete,</hi> without <hi>omnia probate</hi> going before.</p>
               <p>This may ſuffice to offer vnto you a view and conſideration, whether in theſe things you doe well or not, and to aſſwage the partialitie of your followers. I know you haue the gift of Exhortation, and I ſuppoſe charitably, that you haue Zeale, and hate of Sinne; but take heede you want not Knowledge, and Loue: Where the noyſe of Contention is ſo great, that the Truth cannot bee heard, it is to bee wiſhed, the Preachers were dumbe, or the Hearers deafe.</p>
               <p>The laſt cauſe of ſuch Controuerſies, is the vndue publiſhing, and debating of them; which Point needeth no long Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe: Onely I ſay, That Characters of Loue are more proper for Debates of this nature, then Fire-brands of Zeale; That all direct or indirect Glances at mens perſons,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:3358:16"/>
were euer, in the like caſes, diſ-allowed; That whatſoeuer is pretended, the People are not fit Iudges, but rather the quiet pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate Aſſemblyes and Conferences of the Learned: <hi>Qui apud in capacem loquitur non diſſeptat ſed calumniatur,</hi> The Preſſe and Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit would bee freed from theſe Contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; neyther Promotion on the one part, or Hate on the other, ſhould continue theſe Challenges, and vnwarrantable Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tells: That further, all Preachers ought to bee of ſuch good temper, that in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Controuerſie, they may in Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and Conſcience, dayly inculcate and beate vpon Peace, Silence, and Ceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation.</p>
               <p>But becauſe I ſhall haue occaſion to ſpeake of this more fully hereafter, I end the firſt Part of this Diſcourſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:3358:17"/>
               <head>THE SECOND PART.</head>
               <p>IT is not vnknowne to you, how dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and hurtfull the effects of the long ſtirres about the Gouernment of the Church of <hi>Scotland</hi> haue been and had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in Church and State, if the ſedulous A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimaduerſions of a wiſe and fore-ſeeing King had not preuented the ſame: I ceaſe to ſpeake of the ſcandall that hath beene giuen to Religion thereby; how many wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked or ignorant people haue beene confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in Atheiſme, how many weake Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans haue beene diſcouraged in the progreſſe of their Profeſſion, what Sects and bad O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions haue growne vp in corners; theſe that ſhould (and without doubt would) haue repreſſed them, being by Domeſticall Brawles thwarted and hindered. All of ſound iudgement may perceiue what ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage the common Enemy hath taken,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:3358:17"/>
that by ſuch prepoſterous Anarchie, Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning was not onely contemned, but the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thereof diminiſhed, the ancient Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline of the Church ouerthrowne, the Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant made Iudgers of the Rewards of Learning, and the Learned Fathers of the Church, Markes for Licentious Youths, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with Malice, to ſhoot at. The height of this Fury hath extended it ſelfe beyond Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, Tumult, and Scandall: how oft haue theſe tumultuous Practices reached to the height of Leaſe-Maieſty, by intending to conferre your head-leſſe Gouernment on whom you pleaſed, and how you pleaſed, without the Authoritie of any Supreme Power?</p>
               <p>If I might inſtance this, by bringing thoſe vpon the Stage, whoſe Errors you haue followed, rather then their Goodneſſe; I might aske you, what <hi>Fennor</hi> did in his Booke entituled <hi>Axiomata Coelestis Canaan? Beza</hi> in his Booke <hi>de Iure Magiſtratuum in ſubditos? Coppinger</hi> and his followers, in <hi>England?</hi> Or, to come home to our ſelues, what did <hi>Knox</hi> in his Letter written from <hi>Diepe,</hi> or in his foure inuenomed Poſitions,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:3358:18"/>
blowne out by the ſecond blaſt of his foule-breathed Trumpet?</p>
               <p>To deſcend and come to our owne Times; mine owne Eyes did behold that bold head-leſſe Inſurrection, knowne by the ſeuenteenth of September: But pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be God, that Fire was ſoone quench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and that Fruit rotten, before it was ripe; although ſome of the Prime No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie were inuited, or rather coniured (if it had beene poſſible) to take Armes in defence of your lame Cauſe. But let that blacke prodigious Day bee inuolued in darke Hieroglyphicks, and buried in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall ſilence, leaſt future Ages heare of it, or <hi>Erostratus</hi> complayne, that hee is rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed of his Fame, for burning <hi>Diana's</hi> Temple.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, and more lately, from the aſhes of theſe combuſtible Practices, did (Phoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nix-like) ariſe that deformed wreſted Pamphlet, maliciouſly diſperſed, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie learnedly confuted and defaced by that Reuerend Father, Doctor <hi>Lindſay,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Brighen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But here I will ſtay my hand, and play
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:3358:18"/>
no more at this Weapon, leaſt I turne the Point againſt my ſelfe, or by thruſting home, giue the Veine to ſome of your Vitall parts. You know my meaning: they were not the greateſt ſinners, vpon whom the Tower of <hi>Siloah</hi> did fall, <hi>Vnus peccat al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter plectitur;</hi> but I will gently cloſe with you in generall tearmes, and onely tell you, That theſe Ryots of ſingular Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie were ſufficient to haue exaſperated the moſt mercifull Prince to haue rooted out the memorie of ſuch Spirits, who (vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretext of Reformation) neuer aymed at other end (in contempt of Regall Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie) then Tranſlation of Church-Gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to confuſed Paritie, orderleſſe Synods, and to Mechanicke Parochiall Seſſions. What this Reformation did profit, in buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Gods houſe, or repayring of it (as you pretended) and what ſtrange fruits it had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced before this time, if God by his ſeruant, our Soueraigne, had not wrung the Sword out of your hand, let ſound Iudgement giue Verdict. If you will goe a little along with me, and ſuruey vpon what grounds theſe proceedings &amp; miſdemeanors were builded,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:3358:19"/>
you ſhall finde they had none at all, but ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginary Speculation, vnable to vphold a quiet minde, much leſſe, both Church and State. Firſt, there can bee nothing more abſurd, more againſt all Law, Practice, and Reaſon, then the paritie of Church-Gouernment, or Parochiall Iudicature, which you haue ſo long maintained, and which was vpon falſe Grounds broached, to ouerthrow the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and auert the ancient Diſcipline of the Church. To make this cleare, I aske you, if there can be any Gouernment with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Superioritie and Diſtinction of Places? Can Ciuill or Spirituall Eſtates bee better gouerned, then by one armed with Power and Eminencie aboue others? Is not Gods owne Citie, Spirituall <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> a gathering and vniting of Saints into a Diuine Pollicy, whereof the forme is Order; which, as in all actions, ſo in the Gouernment of the Church is moſt neceſſary? Hence <hi>Paul</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyceth of the <hi>Coloſsians</hi> Faith and Order. Looke backe againe, and behold, when Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God gaue Magiſtrates and Lawes to his Church, hee appointed vnder the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Magiſtrate one High Prieſt, to haue
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:3358:19"/>
the Superintendencie of the Affaires of the Church, and vnder him diuerſe Heads and Diuiſions, that Decencie and Order might be preſerued, and Confuſion ſhunned. This ſuperioritie of Prieſthood continued till the new Couenant of Grace; in all which time, if equalitie of Prieſts had beene conducible to the Weale of the Church, without doubt the Lord of the Church would haue eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed it.</p>
               <p>Secondly, after this Ceremoniall Law, our Sauiour Chriſt ruled his Church as chiefe Biſhop of our Soules: hee adioyned no El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to himſelfe; at his death hee gaue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to his Diſciples, to rule the Churches where they ſhould gouerne, throughout the World. Wee reade, that they did excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate alone, that they did ordaine Miniſters alone, and did by ſupreme Authority rule both the Affaires and Goods of the Church. <hi>Beza</hi> confeſſeth, that <hi>Peter</hi> alone ſtrucke <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanias</hi> and <hi>Saphira,</hi> that <hi>Paul</hi> ordayned <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> that hee preſcribed Lawes to them and their Churches; this plat-forme of Paritie was not ſo much as heard of in the time of Perſecution. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> did
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:3358:20"/>
write to the Biſhops of <hi>Epheſus</hi> and <hi>Smyrna,</hi> and to ſeuerall Biſhops of other Churches; to them hee giueth Directions, and them hee reprooueth: which had beene very vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitting, if his Authority had not beene a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue other Miniſters. All Records wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that ſeuerall Biſhops ſucceeded the Apoſtles at <hi>Rome, Constantinople, Ieruſalem, Antioch, Alexandria,</hi> and other places: All the Councells giue preheminence to Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops; and to the Councells, the Fathers conſent.</p>
               <p>To come to later times, they whom you magnifie aboue all others, did proteſt by their Writings, That if Biſhops would leaue Superſtition, and embrace the true Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they would moſt willingly ſubmit themſelues to their Epiſcopall Iuriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as moſt godly and expedient for the Church. <hi>Melancthon</hi> did teſtifie much to this purpoſe, ſaying, That if the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of Biſhops were reiected, a greater Tyrannie would follow. <hi>Zancheus</hi> greatly extolled Biſhops; <hi>Bullinger, Glocer,</hi> and diuerſe other Learned Proteſtants in <hi>Sweth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Germanie,</hi> with <hi>Camerarius</hi> and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:3358:20"/>
                  <hi>Sturmius,</hi> did the like. <hi>Beza</hi> himſelfe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playneth, That his wordes againſt <hi>Roman</hi> Biſhops were wreſted againſt our Biſhops. But ſuppoſe, that <hi>Beza, Daneus, Carpenter, Golart, Perot, Tauergues, Polan, Snecan,</hi> and the like, haue written all which you would haue maintayned, or doe yet hold; ſhall the Church of <hi>Great Brittaine</hi> allow what they haue written, for Oracles? No; there is no reaſon they ſhould: For who would not bee aſhamed to oppoſe thoſe, and their followers, to the practice of the Primitiue Church, of Ieſus Chriſt, his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, Fathers, Councells, Canons, to all Writings of Antiquity, and to the moſt part of our owne Times? All theſe, by Practice or Decrees, haue annulled Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, and conſequently, all kinde of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment grounded vpon it: All Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall Courſes haue cenſured againſt you; the Parliaments (the moſt Honourable Courts in the Ile of <hi>Great Brittaine,</hi> or elſe-where) haue declared againſt you; the Church Aſſemblyes, wherein as Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers you had Voyces, haue found the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:3358:21"/>
nullitie of your cauſe, and all theſe ioyning in one, haue enioyned you to obedience and conformitie: There reſteth nothing on your ſide, but exclayming, bragging, and libelling, which will neuer be otherwayes cenſured by the Wiſe, then the fumoſities of idle Dreame-venting Braynes, who aſſuming to themſelues an vncontrouled Liberty, leaues all Lawes without defence, and expoſeth Magiſtracie to Obloquie, at their pleaſure. But (as all Legiſts and Schoole-men determine) priuate, much leſſe publike Lawes are neyther groſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to bee ieaſted at, careleſly diſgraced, or fondly to bee dealt withall. Conſider warily of this Point, leaſt Iuſtice cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect ſuch by Roddes, as will not bee ruled by Reaſon. So I come to the Third Part of my Taske, and then to an end.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:3358:21"/>
               <head>THE THIRD PART.</head>
               <p>I Haue ſhortly leuelled at, if not hit the moſt materiall Accidents and Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of the Controuerſies which long haue troubled the Peace of our Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> with their bad Effects; and how contrary your oppoſition is to the beſt Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions of former times. Now, after I haue runne poſte through the Fauours of your gracious Soueraigne, I will vnfold my ſincere Wiſhes, and ſo cloſe vp all. His Maieſties prouident care fore-ſeeing, that your violent Platformes would in the end procure the ouerthrow of your cauſe, did ſo long giue way to your inconſiderate pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, till without greater inconuenience to the Church and State, hee could not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare to repreſſe them: in which courſe, I pray you conſider with mee, what Legall courſe hath his Maieſty taken, what Lenitie
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:3358:22"/>
hath hee vſed, what mollifying Balmes of louing Admonition hath hee applyed to ſo long feſtred Sores: Hee hath called many Generall and Prouinciall Aſſemblyes, for ſettling or remoouing many needleſſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſies amongſt you: Hee hath in Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Perſon beene preſent with you, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded you by many Learned Orations, graue Exhortations, and Princely Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions: Hee hath oft times confuted your vngrounded Aſſertions with Reaſon, when hee might haue repreſſed them by his Royall Authority. What vnſeemely miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demeanour wee haue ſeene in the preſence of ſuch a King, my Penne without bluſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is not able to expreſſe: Yet theſe hath his more then Humane Clemencie ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſt, and by the Load-ſtone of infallible Demonſtrations and inuincible Arguments hath drawne the moſt Iudicious and Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned amongſt you to aſſent to the Truth, and leaue ſuch factious courſes; Witneſſe hereof, were Learned Maſter <hi>Rollocke,</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Nicholſon,</hi> and Maſter <hi>Cooper</hi> (whoſe Workes will pleade their cauſe:) The firſt of theſe, vpon his Death-bed did expoſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:3358:22"/>
with his deareſt Friends, how much your hard cenſure of his honeſt Labours in the Affaires of the Church, had ſhorte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his dayes: The laſt two, after they were preferred to the place of Biſhops, and euer before had painefully laboured in the Lords Harueſt, were ſo detracted by your vniuſt Calumnies, and profited ſo little in their ſincere Intentions, that very Griefe in the Autumne of their age did conſummate their dayes: But yet if I ſhould inſiſt vpon his Maieſties Clemencie towards you, I ſhould exceede my limitted Taske. Hee hath ſpared the Liues of ſuch of you, as were guilty of High Treaſon; hee hath, vpon ſubmiſſion, recalled ſuch as were baniſhed, and eyther reſtored them to their owne, or better Places. Finally, hee hath left nothing vndone, that may make his Kingly Wiſedome admired, his Mercie aduaunced, and you, in caſe of further Contumacie, vncapable of the like Royall Fauour hereafter. I ſpeake not this, to aggrauate your Faults, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fawningly to inſinuate vpon Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie; but leaſt any of you ſhould ſurmiſe
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:3358:23"/>
that you haue beene wronged, that the Lawes haue beene rigorouſly extended a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you, or that his Maieſties proceedings hath beene iniurious towards you. But as I am in good hope of you, ſo my earneſt Wiſhes are, that my friendly counſaile may ſeize on your future actions. You know, or may know, that hitherto you haue onely procured a fruitleſſe Reformation, and in the end (without doubt) you will bee the cauſe of greater Euils, if by more whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome aduice you obuiate not the Dangers to which your inconſiderate Zeale hath ſubiected you; the Axe of Iuſtice threate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the Roote of the fruitleſſe Tree of your diſobedience, and eminent puniſhment of your ſcandalous behauiour hangeth ouer your heads: there reſteth nothing then, but that you lay aſide all ſuch deceiuable Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions and priuate Affections, as taints you eyther with Schiſme or Diſloyaltie; that you ſay to the Church, You are our Mother, wee owe you Honour; to the King, You are our Soueraigne and Gods Vice-gerent, wee owe you Allegeance. In ſo doing, you ſhall find, that ſome few enſuing yeeres ſhall produce
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:3358:23"/>
more profitable and plentifull Fruit in Church and Common-wealth, then all the Brawles and ſhewes of Puritie haue done theſe fiftie yeeres paſt. Examine well what I haue ſayd, and my hopes are, that the moſt Factious amongſt you will bee reclay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to the right way, which is all that I deſire, and that the peaceable maintenance of the State enforceth: But if you will paue your hearts with the inſenſibilitie of what you ought to doe, by ſeeking the diſturbance of the Church, and vnquietneſſe of the State, then iudge impartially, and you will eaſily perceiue what muſt follow.</p>
               <p>It is as cleare as the Sunne, that ſuch inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie is not longer to be ſuffered, That the chiefe Tenents of your Opinions are eyther wilfully blinded, or naturally ignorant; That by maintayning theſe ſingular or fond con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions, you abandon the Truth, trouble the Peace of the Church, are offenſiue to the State, and are lyable to the ſeuerity of Iuſtice. Remember, that the purity of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of our Religion conſiſteth in our Faith and Baptiſme, not in our Ceremonie or Policy, about which you haue ſo long
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:3358:24"/>
with loſſe contended. If you will conſider the ſlowneſſe to ſpeake, ſo much commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by Saint <hi>Iames,</hi> our long entertayned Controuerſies would grow together; but more ſpecially, if you would leaue the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular and ouer-weening Opinions of theſe Times, and renew the bleſſed Proceedings of the Apoſtles and Fathers of the Church: which was, in the like or greater Caſes, not to enter into Aſſertions and Poſitions, but to deliuer Councell and Aduice; wee ſhould neede no other remedy at all: <hi>Si eadem con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulis frater quae affirmas, debetur conſulenti reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentia, cum non debeatur fides affirmanti.</hi> Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then <hi>Pericles,</hi> when hee intended to ſpeake publikely, entreated his Gods (not without reaſon) That no vnprouident Word might eſcape his mouth; for the Lunacie of Wit is better purged, the Inflamation of the Tongue better cured, and the Venome of the Heart more exhaled with one Ounce of Good Thought, and a Scruple of <hi>Pythago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricum Silentium,</hi> then with all the <hi>Turbith, Agaricke, Sarco colla,</hi> and <hi>Scammonie</hi> of <hi>Dioſcorides, Rheubarbe</hi> of <hi>Pontus, Manna</hi> of <hi>Calabria;</hi> yea, then with all the contentious
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:3358:24"/>
babbling of <hi>Babel.</hi> Wherefore my deare Countreymen and Brethren, ſince the Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents are the things that breede the Perill, and not the Subſtance; That the Truth is ſcandalized, the long patience of a mercifull and Religious King abuſed; and that, in your former obſtinacy, your wilfulneſſe hath betrayed your Wits, and in the end will draw on your ouerthrow, vpon your Enemyes Triumphs: it is time you yeeld your ſelues conformable to the Ordinances of the Church, eſtabliſhed by Supreme Power, that there were an end of ſuch vncharitable Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and vnedifying Doctrine, wherewith the moſt part of your Pulpits haue been long loaden; of ſuch immodeſt &amp; deformed maner of Writing, wherewith idle Pamphlets haue beene dayly ſo ſtuft, that matters of Religion haue been handled with irreligious hands in the Stile of Stage; all reuerent compaſſion to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Euils forgotten, &amp; Religion turned into a Comedy or Satyre. But alas, to lance wounds with a laughing countenance, to intermixe Scripture and ſcurrility ſometime in one ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, is a thing farre from the deuout reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of a Chriſtian, and ſcarce beſeeming the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:3358:25"/>
regard of a ſober man; <hi>Non eſt maior confuſio quam ſe<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ij &amp; ioci,</hi> The Maieſty of Religion, and the contempt of things ridiculous, are things as farre diſtant as may be.</p>
               <p>Two ſpeciall cauſes of Atheiſme haue I euer obſerued to be curious; Controuerſies, and Prophane Scoffing: by the one, appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the Miſerie of the Curious; and by the other, the Marks of the Fooliſh. What pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion theſe two, ioyned in one, will make, iudge you? As I allow neyther the one, nor the other; ſo doe I not commend ſuch as fight with eyther of them at their owne Weapon: For I eſteeme it Wiſedome and Religion, that a Foole is to bee anſwered, but not by becomming more fooliſh, and like vnto him: That the Matter which is handled, is to be valued, and not the Perſon; <hi>Dum de bonis contendimus in malis conſentimus.</hi> If Diſgraces to your owne Perſons, jibbing at your owne Writings, ſo mightily mooue you; imagine that in others, which you feele in your ſelues: and if you take felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to heare well, remember how to ſpeake well. If I were asked of two contentious perſons, who were moſt to bee blamed? I
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:3358:25"/>
ſhould perhaps remember the Prouerbe, That the ſecond Blow maketh the Fray; or the ſaying of an obſcure Fellow, <hi>Qui replicat multiplicat:</hi> But I would determine the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion with <hi>alter principium dedit, alter modum ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtulit,</hi> by the one wee haue a beginning, and by the other wee ſhall neuer haue an end. I know the moſt part, or all the Biſhops and Learned Clergy, neyther allow of ſuch fierie Sermons and ſcandalous Libels, as haue been too commonly vented; or if any fawning perſon haue miſtaken the humours of men in Authority, they haue ſacrificed <hi>Veneri ſuem,</hi> and haue ſought to gratifie them with that which they moſt diſlike: As it had beene good, that ſuch Births had beene choakt at firſt, and neuer ſeene the Sunne; ſo the next is, That ſuch as hereafter be hatched in corners, and put abroad, bee cenſured by all of Vnderſtanding and Conſcience, as the extrauagant Councels of light Perſons: That men be warie how they bee conuerſant in them, except they will depriue themſelues of all ſenſe of Religion: That as ſiniſter imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, or other wrong ends, haue brought them to delight in that vaine; ſo the loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:3358:26"/>
ſight and reprochfull effects may moue ſhame and forbearance.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, I doe exhort you to remooue all Blockes that may encounter your conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, ſpecially that reaſonleſſe Reaſon, That you are tyed by Oath to maintaine your for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Diſcipline in all controuerted Differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. You know (if you would know) that all ſuch Oathes were taken for the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the true Religion, in the puritie of Subſtance, and not in the indifferencies of Pollicy and Ceremonies, which then, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the time, were out of frame: for ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidentall Ceremonies and externall matters of Pollicy are not to be tyed to perpetuitie, eyther in Eccleſiaſticall or Ciuill Eſtate, but may bee promoued or altered at all times from worſe to better, according to the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Times, and diſcretion of wiſe Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours. Beſides, if you diſclayme not that Oath, you belye <hi>Iohn Knox;</hi> who publiſhed by Writing to the Nobility and Communalty of <hi>Scotland,</hi> That vnlawfull Oathes are not to bee kept (as indeede they are not.) If hee by wreſting that Text, did free ſubiects from their Allegeance to
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:3358:26"/>
their lawfull Princes; why may not lawfull Princes iuſtly vrge it againſt you, in chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenging your lawfull Obedience? Be then no more ſtumbling blockes to the weake, nor breakers of bruiſed Reedes; but Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternes to the Blinde, and Feete to the Lame. Be carefull how you inſtruct Gods People, committed to your charge: Detaſte truly all Badges of Anarchy, and Separation. Haue euer one eye fixed vpon the indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rencie of the things, for which you haue ſo long contended, and another vpon Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to ſupreme Powers, that all incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diarie Fuell of forbidden Zeale remoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, Chriſts ſeameleſſe Coat be no more diuided. You that ſo long haue furniſhed Aduantage to common Enemyes, ſingle now out of the Sheafe one of <hi>Seleucus</hi> Arrowes, and the weakeſt Finger will breake it, whileſt the whole Bundle fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth no ſtreſſe. Let the cooling Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Moderation and Reaſon quench and abate the fire of inordinate Zeale and Contention.</p>
               <p>It was the Imperiall Decree of <hi>Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius,</hi> enacted by the Councell of S. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:3358:27"/>
That all publike ſeuere Sentences ſhould be deferred for thirtie dayes, <hi>Vt ira decocta durior emendari poſsit ſententia.</hi> Qualifie the heat of your paſſions by mature aduice, and Gods preſence will rather accompanie your La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours in ſuch a gentle calme Gale, then in the Fire-flaſhing Thunder of Reuealings, or paſſionate Debates. Separate Selfe-loue, Selfe-will, and Vncharitableneſſe, and you will eaſily be reconciled: <hi>Prima ſanitatis pars est velle ſanari.</hi> Snarle not like Curres, at thoſe that gently ſtroake you on the backe, neyther eate your owne hearts with pale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fac't Enuy, the Impoſtume of the Soule. Remember what Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> ſayth of ſuch vnbrotherly iarres, <hi>Quid facit in corde Chriſtiano Luporum feritas aut canum rabies, qualia ſolet eructare turgens &amp; indigeſta diſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia.</hi> Imitate no more eyther <hi>Moloſſean,</hi> or <hi>Melitean</hi> Dogges, in barking or biting, but reduce all diſ-tuned Strings of Diſcord to the ſweet concent of Chriſtian Harmonie. <hi>Iulius Caeſar</hi> gloryed in nothing more, then in gratifying his Friends, and pardoning his Enemyes: and ſhall Chriſtians bee ſo farre from parallelling ſo rare a Preſident in a
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:3358:27"/>
Pagan, that they ſhall contentiouſly calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niate their Leaders or Brethren? Farre be it from them: The Myſticall Body of Chriſt is all faire, and this Beauty conſiſts in the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietie of Colours, and concinne diſpoſition of Parts; no Member muſt mutter againſt the Head or Fellow, or affect a Hotch-potch Paritie, leaſt they martyr or marre Chriſts Body, which is fitly knit together in euery Ioynt, that miniſtreth to another.</p>
               <p>O then, my Brethren, ſeaſon your Actions, Sermons, Papers, and Diſcourſe, with the Salt of Wiſdome, in lieu of vnbrotherly Practices, reaſonleſſe Rayling, vnmannerly Writing, and bitter Language: the firſt is begotten of Peace, entertaineth Peace, nouriſheth Vertue, inſtructeth Error, and maketh the Life ſauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie; but the ſecond are the Gall of Wit, the Bloud-ſuckers of Charity, and the Semina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of all Euils: <hi>Habete in vobis Sal &amp; pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem habebitis inter vos;</hi> When Wiſedome is your Guide, you ſhall reade your owne Infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities in other mens Falls; metamorphoſe the Fury of <hi>Aiax,</hi> into the Wit of <hi>Vlyſſes;</hi> exchange Rebellious Mutinies into Filiall Obedience: and then ſhall your aduiſed Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:3358:28"/>
and wary Circumſpection arme you againſt all Aſſaults and Accidents; that as we are the Sonnes of one ſpirituall Father &amp; Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, God and the Church; Seruants of one Maſter, our Soueraigne here vpon Earth, and hope to be co-heires hereafter in Heauen: ſo wee may bee cloathed with one Liuery of Vnanimitie, Peace, and Loue; That like the Starres of Heauen, euery one in his owne ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and order may fight Gods Battels, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of our ſacred Faith, and obſeruance of our Allegeance to God and his Vice-gerents; That in caſe of ceſſation of Foraine Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Embrewments in others Bloud (which God graunt) we, and all that will fight vnder Chriſts Banner, may lay hold vpon the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie occaſion of <hi>Mahometan</hi> Sciſſure. And in this, and what I haue written, I pray vnto the Lord of Life to ſecond my good Wiſhes, and encreaſe both in you and me that Loue, without which, all that wee doe, is vnprofitable. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:3358:28"/>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:3358:29"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:3358:29"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
